Pueblo, Colo. Christ Congregational Church records, 1955-2023.
Congregational Library & Archives
Pueblo, Colo. Christ Congregational Church records, 1955-2023.
RG5485
Congregational Library & Archives
4.06 Cubic Feet
(5 boxes)
In 1955, Rev. Hoy of the First Congregational Church in Pueblo suggested that the residents of the developing Belmont neighborhood should consider establishing a "liberal" protestant church. The Christ Congregational Church was formally incorporated on February 11, 1957. The church building was designed by Elizabeth Wright Ingraham and Gordon Ingraham and construction was completed on the building in August, 1957. The church's membership rose significantly during the 1960s and dropped during the 1970s. During the 1980s, Pueblo's first female minister, Rev. Karen Sorensen, was installed as pastor of the church. During the 1990s, the church adopted the Open and Affirming designation. The membership declined during the 2000s and eventually dissolved in 2023. This collection contains records related to the administration and community of the church and includes meeting minutes, annual reports, financial and building records, membership records, and newsletters.
Christ Congregational Church (Pueblo, Colo.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Christ Congregational Church in October 2023; 2023-51.
Historical Note
During the 1950s, Pueblo, Colorado, saw a massive 43% increase in its population. In 1955, in the midst of the population boom, Rev. Hoy of the First Congregational Church in Pueblo suggested that the residents of the developing Belmont neighborhood should consider establishing a "liberal" protestant church. In 1956, Rev. William Shafer was called to eventually lead this church. The first church service, held in the basement of the parsonage, the first building constructed for the church, on September 16, 1956. The church was formally incorporated on February 11, 1957 as the Christ Congregational Church.
The church building was designed by Elizabeth Wright Ingraham, the granddaughter of Frank Lloyd Wright, and her husband, Gordon Ingraham. The original design called for a triangular building with three distinct wings, though only the first wing was ever constructed. Construction of the building was completed in August, 1958. The first worship, and dedicatory service, was held in the newly constructed church building on September 14, 1958.
The church's membership rose significantly during the 1960s, to a height of 600 members in 1963. The church community was very active at the time, with three youth groups, a Boy Scouts troop, a couple's club, and the Women's Fellowship. The 1970s saw a downturn in membership. During the 1980s, Pueblo's first female minister, Rev. Karen Sorensen, was installed as pastor of the church. While some members left over the decision to install Sorensen, the church overall saw growth during her ministry. The early 1990s saw a similar situation with the church's eventual decision to adopt the UCC's Open and Affirming designation; while some members left over the decision, other came to join the church owing to its liberal designation.
The late 1990s and 2000s saw the church's membership shrink significantly again, owing in part to changes in Belmont's demographics and controversies that arose around Rev. Sorensen that precipitated her eventual departure from the church. The church continued to serve the Pueblo community as a liberal protestant church until 2023 when the church voted to dissolve.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the administrative records of the Christ Congregational Church in Pueblo, Colorado, as well as records documenting the church community. The collection includes meeting minutes, annual reports, baptismal records, membership records and directories, financial records, building records and blueprints, photographs, records of events, and newsletters.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into the three series, and three subseries, listed below. Within each series and subseries, materials have been arranged in chronological order and topic, when appropriate.
Series 1: Church records, 1956-2023
Series 2: Financial and building records, 1955-2023
Series 3: Community records, 1956-2022
Subseries 1: Photographic materials, 1956-2014
Subseries 2: Membership records, 1957-2020
Subseries 3: Events and programs, 1957-2022
Technical Requirements
A computer with a disk drive is required to directly view digital contents found on compact disks.
Baptismal records.; Church buildings.; Church finance.; Church membership.; Church newsletters.; Church records and registers.; Photograph albums.; Christ Congregational Church (Pueblo, Colo.)
- Church records, 1956 2023; 1956-2023; 46 Folders; 1 Volume
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to the administrative history of the Christ Congregational Church in Pueblo, Colorado. This series includes church council meeting minutes, annual reports, committee minutes and reports, church histories, letters and communications, and records related to the closure of the church.
  - Miscellaneous communications, 1956 1998; 1956-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Church register, 1957 1969; 1957-1969 (Box 1, Volume 1)
    Separated Materials
    Some loose materials were removed from this register and placed in the folder titled "Membership updates, 1969-1970" for the purposes of preservation.
  - Church history, 1957 1980; 1957-1980 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Board of trustees minutes, 1957 1960; 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board of trustees minutes, 1980 1983; 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual reports, 1958 1970; 1958-1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual reports, 1971 1986; 1971-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual reports, 1987 2021; 1987-2021 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Stewardship committee records, 1960 1982; 1960-1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - UCC yearbook reports, 1960 1983; 1960-1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Church histories, 1964 2001; 1964-1979, 2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Constitutions and bylaws, 1964 2006; circa 1964-2006 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Diaconate records, 1965 2009; 1965-2009 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Meetings and reports, 1965 1974; 1965-1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Historian's files, 1966 2014; 1966-2014 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Search committee records, 1981 1992; 1981-1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Church policies, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Minutes and reports, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Minutes and reports, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Minutes and reports, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Minutes and reports, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Minutes and reports, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Minutes and reports, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Minutes and reports, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Minutes and reports, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Minutes and reports, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Minutes and reports, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Minutes and reports, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Minutes and reports, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Minutes and reports, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Minutes and reports, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Minutes and reports, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Minutes and reports, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Minutes and reports, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Minutes and reports, 2018 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Minutes and reports, 2019 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Minutes and reports, 2020 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Minutes and reports, 2021 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous communications, 2004 2014; 2004-2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Shared ministry committee minutes, 2010 2014; 2010-2014 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Councils, boards, and committees list, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Worship council records, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Communications committee records, 2015 2016; 2015-2016 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Criminal incidents, 2015 2017; 2015-2017 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Chruch dissolution and disbursement, 2023 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Superintendent duties list, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Church goals, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Financial and building records, 1955 2023; 1955-2023; 22 Folders
  This series contains records related to the finances and property of the Christ Congregational Church in Pueblo, Colorado. This series includes financial records, legal property documents, records related to memorials, records related to the sale of property, blueprints and records related to construction and renovations, and capital campaign records.
  - Deeds and ordinances (copies), 1955 1965; 1955-1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Acquisition of property documents, 1955 1965; 1955-1965 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Building plans and specifications, 1957 1992; 1957-1958, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Church building insurance correspondence, 1957 1959; 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Legal records (some copies), 1957 2007; 1957-2007 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Pew construction, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Sale of church land, 1967 1980; 1967-1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Building expansion, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Blueprints, plans, drawings, 1973, undated (Folder 4)
  - Mortgage and property valuation records, 1973 1981; 1973-1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Parsonage sale, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Solar shed construction, 1981 1983; 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Financial reports, 1981 1984; 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Church maintenance calendars, 1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Miscellaneous financial records, 1991 2015; 1991-2015 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Capital campaign planning inquires, 1992 1997; 1992-1997 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Playground drawings, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Legal property documents, 2004 2009; 2004-2009 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - ADA accessibility project, 2010 2014; 2010-2014 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Memorial donations, 2012 2013; 2012-2013 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Church and financial records, 2021 2023; 2021-2023 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Memorials, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Memorial contributions, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Community records, 1956 2022; 1956-2022; 54 Folders; 5 Volumes; 3 Compact Disks
  This series contains records related to the members and community of the Christ Congregational Church in Pueblo, Colorado. This series includes photographs, membership records, such as vital records and member directories, and records related to community events and programs held by the church.
  - Photographic materials, 1956 2014; 1956-2014; 14 Folders; 5 Volumes; 3 Compact Disks
    This subseries contains photographs, and other types of photographic materials, related to the community and members of the Christ Congregational Church in Pueblo, Colorado.
    - Scrapbook vol 1, 1956 2003; 1956-1966, 2003 (Box 4, Volume 2)
    - Scrapbook vol 2, 1958 1982; 1958-1982 (Box 4, Volume 3)
    - Scrapbook vol 3, 1973 1983; 1973-1983 (Box 4, Volume 4)
    - Scrapbook, 1979 1981; 1979-1981 (Box 4, Volume 1)
    - Photographs, 1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Scrapbook, 1983 2009; 1983-1987, 2008-2009 (Box 4, Volume 5)
    - Photograph album (part 1), 1980 1989; circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Photograph album (part 2), 1980 1989; circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Photograph album, 1985 1990; circa 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Photograph album, 1990 1999; circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Photograph album, 1990 1995; circa 1990-1995 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Unorganized photographs, 1990 2009; 1990-2009, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Operation paintbrush photographs, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Construction photographs, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Celebrate! photographs, 2005 2010; 2005-2010 (Box 5, Compact disk 1)
    - RoMoCo summer camp promo, 2011 (Box 5, Compact disk 2)
    - Small church conference pictures, 2012 (Box 5, Compact disk 3)
    - Event photographs, 2013, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Membership collages, 2013, undated (Folder 3)
    - Unorganized photographs, circa 2014, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Family photographs and biographies, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Madrigal pride images, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - John Mareucchio image, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Membership records, 1957 2020; 1957-2020; 12 Folders
    This subseries contains records related to the membership of the Christ Congregational Church in Pueblo, Colorado. This subseries includes membership lists and directories, baptismal records, transfer letters, surveys and results, and profiles about the church.
    - Baptismal records, 1957 1977; 1957-1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Church profiles, 1961 1981; 1961-1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Membership status, 1965 1970; 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Membership updates, 1969 1970; 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      These materials were removed from the back of the "Church register, 1957-1969" for preservation purposes.
    - Member directories, 1971 2006; 1971-2006 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Transfer letters, 1991 2023; 1991-1996, 2023 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Membership lists, 2008 2020; 2008-2020 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Parish profile survey results, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Jeannine Lamb transfer letter, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - New member orientation packet, 2017 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Church survey, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Church brochure, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Events and programs, 1957 2022; 1957-2022; 28 Folders
    This subseries contains records related to events, programs, and various happenings held by the community of the Christ Congregational Church in Pueblo, Colorado. The subseries includes programs, planning documents for events, examples of materials disbursed at events, and records related to various projects undertaken by the church community.
    - Newsletters, 1957 1959; 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Newsletters, 1960 1962; 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Newsletters, 1963 1964; 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Newsletters, 1965 1968; 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Newsletters, 1969 1977; 1969-1977 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Newsletters, 1978 1984; 1978-1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Newsletters, 1985 1989; 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Undated newsletters, 1986 1992; circa 1986-1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Newletters, 1990 1993; 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Newletters, 1994 2000; 1994-2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Newletters, 2001 2005; 2001-2005 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Newsletters, 2006 2010; 2006-2010 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Chrismon ornaments explainer, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Certificates, 1988 2022; 1988, 2021-2022 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Clippings, 1991 2015; 1991-2015 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Open and affirming clippings, 1996 2001; 1996, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 50th anniversary card, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Peppersauce Bottoms project, 2006 2007; 2006-2007 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Bible study materials, 2007 2014; 2007-2014 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Empowering the Small Church conference communications, 2011 2012; 2011-2012 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Empowering the Small Church conference planning, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Empower the Small Church conference materials, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Madrigal dinner, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Non-event fundraiser, 2015 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Transgender day of remembrance program, 2017 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Christmas family worship, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Pastoral column drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Brochure printing files, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)